A Guide to the Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center Papers, 1952-2012
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center Papers, 1952-2012
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-61
2 boxes with the dimensions of 5.5 inches x 10 inches x 15.5 inches, 2 boxes with the dimensions of 4 inches x 16 inches x 20 inches, and 2 boxes with the dimensions of 10.5 inches x 12.5 inches x 16.5 inches
University of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Boxes 1-3 of the collection are open to research; Box 4 contains material that is restricted until 2100; Boxes 5 and 6 are also restricted at this time.
Acquisition Information
The materials were collected by Daniel Cavanaugh from the Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center (KCRC) gymnasium, where they had been stored, and transferred from KCRC on Ivy Road, part of the University of Virginia Health System, to the University of Virginia's Claude Moore Health Sciences Library on 23 April 2014. A second group of records was gathered by Administrative Staff Specialist, Carolyn Craig, and transferred from the Battle Building, the location of the UVA Child Development and Rehabilitation Center, to the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library on 17 July 2014. The collection also includes material transferred to the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library prior to 2014. The exact date and details of this transfer are unknown. These materials are contained in Series I of the collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
For 57 years, the Kluge Children’s Rehabilitation Center (KCRC) provided the region with a wide range of children's rehabilitation and developmental services. As the center attained international acclaim, it began to receive patients from around the world. The establishment of the center reaches back to the 1950s when the University of Virginia (UVA) Department of Orthopedics recognized a need for a children’s treatment facility. Through the efforts of the Department of Orthopedics, funds were raised to build a new center, known as the UVA Rehabilitation Center for Handicapped Children, which opened in November 1957. The center was constructed on the site of the former Rucker Home for Children, an institution established in 1941 for young patients with tuberculosis of the spine. When the Rucker Home, named for its initial benefactor, William J. Rucker, was demolished to make way for the new center, stones from the original house were used to build a wall that bordered the front of the KCRC property along Ivy Road. An orthopedic surgeon at UVA, Dr. Hamilton Allen, became the center’s first director upon its opening in 1957. Some time later, the name of the center was changed to the Children's Rehabilitation Center (CRC), and in 1965 the center became a formal part of the UVA Hospital system.
The facility was renovated in the early 1970s when an education wing, pool, and gymnasium were constructed. Additional improvements were to follow, and after a $2.5 million donation from John and Patricia Kluge, the center was rededicated as the Kluge Children’s Rehabilitation Center (KCRC) in 1988. A second expansion completed in 1989 included a designated outpatient services area. In the late 1980s, with its updated facilities and under the leadership of Medical Director Dr. Sharon Hostler, KCRC adopted a stronger focus on research and clinical training.
During its 57 years in operation, KCRC’s inpatient care treated thousands of children with brain and spine injuries, chronic lung conditions, and serious feeding issues. KCRC’s diverse outpatient services included developmental pediatrics, pediatric orthopedics, and a wide range of disability-specific clinics for diabetes, down syndrome, cerebral palsy, cystic fibrosis, physical and occupational therapy, dentistry, autism, nutrition, and much more. Over the years, KCRC’s focus on family-centered care brought it national attention and tremendous success.
In 2012 KCRC stopped receiving new patients in preparation for the relocation of pediatric services at UVA from the KCRC building on Ivy Road to the Children's Hospital in the Battle Building on West Main Street, adjacent to the main UVA hospital. The move was completed in July 2014. In the new facility, the pediatric care center was renamed the UVA Child Development and Rehabilitation Center.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 64 folders of processed materials. Series I of the collection contains materials related to the University of Virginia (UVA) Children’s Medical Center from 1981 to 1989 and includes mostly news clippings and press releases. These documents were likely collected by various iterations of UVA’s Marketing Communications department, including the Medical Center Information Services, the Medical Center News Office, and the Health Sciences Center News Office, and possibly by other entities affiliated with the Children’s Medical Center and the UVA Hospital. Series II-VII contain materials documenting the work and services of the Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center (KCRC) during its 57 years of operation. These materials include patient care instructions, nursing guidelines, institutional memos, items from various anniversaries and milestone events, news clippings related to KCRC and its patients, and a scrapbook which records a brief history of the center. Series VIII contains a pediatric patient ledger used from 1952-1967 that is restricted until 2100. Series IX contains unprocessed materials which were accessioned with the collection and remain restricted at this time. These unprocessed materials include photographs, slides, negatives, photo CDs, cards and letters, and 10 U-matic tapes.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in nine series, two of which have been further organized into subseries. Materials within each series are arranged chronologically where possible. The series and subseries arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I, Children's Medical Center News Office Papers, 1981-1989
Series II, Instructional Materials for Nurses and Families, circa 1977-2003
Series III, Communications and Programs, 1978-2012
Series IV, KCRC Anniversary Celebrations, 1998-2008
Subseries 1, KCRC 40th Anniversary Materials, 1998
Subseries 2, KCRC 50th Anniversary Materials, 2007-2008
Series V, News clippings, 1986-2012
Subseries 1, KCRC Patient stories, 1986-2010
Subseries 2, General KCRC news stories, 1998-2012
Series VI, KCRC Staff and Facilities Photographs, undated, 2000-2010
Series VII, KCRC Scrapbooks, 1961-1980s
Series VIII, Patient Ledger, 1951-1967
Series IX, Unprocessed Materials, undated
Contents List
- Series I: Children's Medical Center News Office Papers, 1981-1989
  Marketing materials and news clippings dating from 1981 to 1989 related to the Children's Medical Center at UVA.
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1981: Establishment of the Hearthstone Children’s House, 1981 April 14-16 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1985: Committee agenda, correspondence, promotional materials, news clippings, and donors list from the 1985 Children’s Miracle Network Telethon, undated - 1985 July (Box-folder 1:2)
    Also includes a memo on the selection of a new director of the UVA Hospital Child Care Center.
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1985: News clippings on Children’s Rehabilitation Center patients and staff, 1985 August 29 - December 29 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1986: News clippings on UVA-related medical news and Children’s Medical Center-related human interest stories, including: Baby Doe cases and the establishment of the UVA Gait/Motion Analysis Laboratory, 1986 January 16 - February 27 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1986: Press release and news clippings on John and Patricia Kluge’s donation for a new outpatient wing at the Children’s Rehabilitation Center, 1986 March 5-8 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1986: News clippings and press release on the 1986 Children’s Miracle Network Telethon, 1986 May 22 - June 21 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1986: Children’s Rehabilitation Center Medical Experts list, news clippings on UVA gifts and successes, and press release on Kluge’s donation for the CRC, 1986 July - November 25 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1987: News clippings and press releases related to medical news, J.D. and Peggy Swartz’s donation, and the appointment of Ray R. Mishler, Director of Development for the Children’s Medical Center, 1987 January 29 - May 23 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1987: Press release and news clippings on the 1987 Children’s Miracle Network Telethon, and news clipping on the renaming of the Children’s Medical Center, in honor of John Kluge, 1987 May 26 - June 2 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1987: Press release on the Friends Committee of the UVA Children’s Medical Center, and news clippings on Children’s Medical Center patients, 1987 August 7 - December 18 (Box-folder 1:10)
    Press release describes Mr. and Mrs. John D. Bassett joining the Friends Committee of the UVA Children’s Medical Center, chaired by Mrs. William C. Battle, also includes news clippings on the renaming of the Children’s Rehabilitation Center.
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1987: Making Wishes Come True brochure, 1987 (Box-folder 1:11)
    Wish list of hospital equipment and CMC fundraising causes.
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1988: Press release and news clippings on the “Kid Safe” educational event, 1988 March 16 - April 4 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1988: News clippings on the rededication of the Kluge Children’s Rehabilitation Center, 1988 April 16-18 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1988: News clippings on fundraising and the 1988 Children’s Miracle Network Telethon, 1988 April 20 - June 18 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Children’s Medical Center News Office Papers 1989: News clippings on UVA news, Armenian earthquake victims, and the 1989 Children’s Miracle Network Telethon, 1989 January 29 - June 8 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Series II: Instructional materials for nurses and families, 1977-2003(?)
  - Nursing instructions for children in traction; adapted from Hilt & Schmitt, Pediatric Orthopedic Nursing, 1975, The C.V. Mosby Company, 1977 August 7, 23 pages (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Discharge instructions for construction of the Split Bradford Frame; written by Nancy E. Hilt, R.N., M.S.N., and Discharge plans for parents of children with seizures, written by Rita McGowan, R.N., 1979, 4 pages, 12 pages (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Parents’ guide for congenital dislocated hips: taking your child home in traction; developed by Janet Paarlberg, R.N., M.S.N., C.R.R.N.circa 1992, 8 pages (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Acquired brain injury: A guide for families, created by Pat Morris, R.N. and Judy Gary, M. Ed., 1996 July, 20 pages (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Kluge Children’s Rehabilitation Center Family Handbook, circa 1996-2003, 16 pages (Box-folder 1:20)
- Series III: Communications and Programs, 1978-2012
  Materials generated by or for the Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center (or the UVA Health System) relating to medical services and daily activities.
  - Project Report for Children’s Rehabilitation Center O.P.D. Addition from Bruce C. Baldwin, Michael W. Hakala, M.D., Sharon L. Hostler, M.D., Cynthia B. Ligon, and Larry A. Yatchum to Dr. Donald Wright, Mr. Hal Javins, and Ms. Madeline Dickman, 1978 June 20, 1 TD 5 pages (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Praise for KCRC inpatient staff members, 1995 May, 1 TD 1 page (Box-folder 1:22)
  - The Aladdin Project: A Plan for Change, Patient Care Services Division, UVA Health Sciences Center, circa 1996, 28 pages (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Letter from Mary Bettner, R.N., M.S.N., JMU Clinical Instructor, to the staff of KCRC, 1996 October 8, 1 TLS 1 page (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Centerpieces, Volume 1, Issue 17 (KCRC Newsletter), 1998 September 30, 1 Facsimile 3 pages (Box-folder 1:25)
  - The Heart of the Matter, Newsletter of the Auxiliary & Volunteers, 2004 Fall, 4 pages (Box-folder 1:26)
  - KCRC Meditation Place Dedication program, 2006 February 3 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - KCRC News, Volume 1, Issue 1, 2006 June 9, 3 pages (Box-folder 1:28)
  - KCRC Holiday photo cards, 2006, undated, 1 Color Photo 7.5 x 9.5, 1 Color Photo 4 x 6 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Itinerary for a visit from The Children’s Institute of Pittsburg, PA, to KCRC, 2007 March 19, 1 TD 1 page (Box-folder 1:30)
  - KCRC Holiday Talent Show materials, 2007 December 19, 3 TD 5 pages (Box-folder 1:31)
    Talent Show program; “Take Me Home, Ivy Road” lyrics, adapted by Rich Stevenson, performed by Los Homely Boys at the 2007 KCRC Holiday Talent Show; KCRC Christmas card project instructions from Kelly Bell
  - Email from James P. Nataro, M.D., Ph.D., M.B.A., to the UVA Department of Pediatrics regarding the end of inpatient services at KCRC, 2012 July 19, 1 TL 1 page (Box-folder 1:32)
- Series IV: KCRC Anniversary Celebrations, 1998-2008
  Items related to the 40th and 50th KCRC anniversary celebrations
  - KCRC 40th Anniversary Materials, 1998
    - Letter from Peppy G. Linden to the staff of KCRC, 1998 October 11, 1 Facsimile TLS 2 pages (Box-folder 1:33)
    - “Happy Birthday KCRC” announcements printed in The Daily News Leader of Staunton, VA, and The Daily Progress of Charlottesville, VA, 1998 October 11, News clippings (Box-folder 1:34)
    - Media Advisory on KCRC anniversary activities, 1998 October 13, 1 TD 2 pages (Box-folder 1:35)
    - Programs, announcements, and dinner cards from the “Happy Birthday KCRC! Under the Tents Celebration and Festivities,” 1998 October 13-15 (Box-folder 1:36)
    - KCRC tributes written by Peter Blasco, Ron Adams, and John Blanco, 1998, undated, 1 TDS 2 pages, 1 AD 2 pages, 1 TDS 1 page (Box-folder 1:37)
    - Letter from Paul Clinton Harris, Sr., member of the Virginia House of Delegates, to the Staff of KCRC, 1998 October 14, 1 TLS 1 page, 1 envelope (Box-folder 1:38)
    - Photos from KCRC’s 41st birthday celebration printed in The Daily Progress, 1998 October 16, News clipping (Box-folder 1:39)
  - KCRC 50th Anniversary Materials, 2007-2008
    - “The University of Virginia Kluge Children’s Rehabilitation Center Celebrates Its 50th,” from the American Academy of Pediatrics Virginia Chapter Newsletter, 2007 Fall, 2 pages (Box-folder 1:40)
    - Slide of KCRC 50th Anniversary painting by Kacey Sydnor Carneal, 2007, 1 color slide 4 x 5 (Box-folder 1:41)
    - Commemorative 50th anniversary card from Dr. Michelle Kuperminc to the KCRC inpatient nursing staff, 2007(?), 1 AC 4.75 x 6.25 (Box-folder 1:42)
    - KCRC 50th Anniversary Celebration flyer and schedule, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 1:43)
    - Invitations and programs from the KCRC 50th anniversary celebration, 2007 November 16 - 2008 April 17 (Box-folder 1:44)
      KCRC Children Celebrate! for patients and families, 2007 November 16
      Celebrating Friends and Colleagues, 2007 December 13
      Celebrating Staff Present and Past, 2008 April 11
      Celebrating Our Community, 2008 April 17
    - RSVP lists and guest lists from KCRC 50th anniversary events, 2007 December 13 - 2008 April 17 (Box-folder 1:45)
    - KCRC 50th anniversary gift items: commemorative pin, gift tag, flower seeds, paper giraffes, and photographs of gift bags, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 1:46)
    - Written memories from KCRC staff for the 50th anniversary celebration, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 1:47)
    - “50 years of help, rehabilitation: Kluge children’s center focuses on the whole family,” from The Daily Progress, 2007 December 22, 1 news clipping, 1 facsimile, 1 print-out (Box-folder 1:48)
- Series V: News clippings, 1986-2012
  News clippings mostly taken from Virginia newspapers related to KCRC milestones, activities, and patients.
  - KCRC Patient stories, 1986-2010
    Stories printed in The Shenandoah Free Press, The Richmond Times-Dispatch, Times Community Newspapers, The Connection, The Roanoke Times, The Bristol News, The Madison County Eagle, The Daily Progress, The Warren Sentinel, The Daily News Leader, The Central Virginian, and others.
    - News clippings: KCRC patient stories, 1986 December 3 - 1996 May 26 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - News clippings: KCRC patient stories, 1996 July 1 - 1997 January 1 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - News clippings: KCRC patient stories, 1998 October 16 - 2005 April 21 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - News clippings: KCRC patient stories, 2005 May 6 - 2007 December 30 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - News clippings: KCRC patient stories, 2009 October 11 - 2010 October 20 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - General KCRC news stories, 1998-2012
    - “UVA eyes children’s hospital additions,” from The Daily Progress, and “Club donates bears to children,” from The Daily Progress, 1998 November 3, 2004 October 29 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - “Gap shows gift-giving always in style,” from The Daily Progress, and “UVA’s Kluge Center Named Top in State,” from NBC29 News, 2005 March 29, 2009 June 7 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - “John Kluge Dies at 95,” from NBC29 News, “Care to stop for few Kluge patients,” and “Sad to See Closing of UVA’s KCRC,” from The Daily Progress, 2010 September 8, 2012 July (Box-folder 2:8)
- Series VI: KCRC Staff and Facilities Photographs undated, 2000-2010
  Images of KCRC staff members and the KCRC building, includes photographs of a design model for an expansion to KCRC.
  - KCRC staff photographs, undated (Box-folder 2:9)
    Staff pictured in photographs includes: Margo Davis, R.N., April Garrison, R.N., Anna DeLong, Natalie Munger, R.N., Chaplain Julie Perry, Anne Jacobs, Anna King, Laurie Sewell, Melissa Murphy. Some subjects unidentified.
  - KCRC staff photographs, undated (Box-folder 2:10)
    Staff pictured in photographs includes: Becky (?), Stephanie (?), Jerry (?), Leon (?). Some subjects unidentified.
  - KCRC staff photographs, undated (Box-folder 2:11)
    Staff pictured in photographs includes: Margaret Patton, R.N. Some subjects unidentified.
  - KCRC facilities photographs, undated, 2000 (Box-folder 2:12)
    Includes photos of a KCRC expansion design model and a photo of the UVA hospital credited to Mike Higgins, 2000
  - KCRC patient artwork, undated, 2010 (Box-folder 2:13)
- Series VII: KCRC Scrapbooks 1961-1980s
  - Scrapbook 1, 1961-1981, bulk 1976-1978, Red album 12.5 x 16.5 (Box-folder 3:1)
    News clippings of Children's Rehabilitation Center patient stories and UVA hospital news
  - Scrapbook 2, circa 1970-1988, Brown album 12.5 x 15 (Box-folder 3:2)
    Documents a brief history of the Children's Rehabilitation Center and its services and mission
- Series VIII: Patient Ledger 1951-1967
  Access restricted until 2100.
  - Pediatric Diagnosis Ledger, 1951-1967, Brown covers, metal bindings 12 x 18 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Series IX: Unprocessed materials undated (Box 5-6)
  Two boxes of unprocessed materials include photographs, slides, negatives, photo CDs, cards and letters, and 10 U-matic tapes.
  Access restricted.